A Guide to the Joel Chandler Harris Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #6322-b
Joel Chandler Harris Collection 1881-1907
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
6322-b
49 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit, 1964 Oct 20
Item Listing
- Manuscripts
  - "A Negro Love Song" and "Hog Feeder's Song", [c. 1892]; AMsS/AMs, 5 p.
    [Songs; manuscript of two Afro-American songs with a one page introduction on the remarkable range of a hog-caller's voice.]
  - "The Plow-Hand's Song", AMsS, 1 p.
    [Song]
  - "A Latch fer de gate...", n.d.; AMsS, 1 p.
    [Poem]
- Letters
  - Joel Chandler Harris to Jeannette L. Gilder, 1881 Oct 10; ALS, 1 p. w/env
    [Sending something for
    The Critic
    asks her to return it with a "literary note" if she cannot use it; praises a sketch of Uncle Remus.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to Unknown, 1881 Dec 28; ALS, 1 p.
    [Says that
    The Century
    has first refusal; can be published in book form after the serial rights have been exercised.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to B[enjamin] H. [Ticknor], 1884 Mar 15; ALS, 1 p.
    [Writes him about a new short book; could have "A Plot for a Play" finished in a week; wants
    Blue Dave
    sent to Scotland for copyright; asks for the opinion of the firm's reader on
    . Signed "Uncle Remus."]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to William Carey, 1884 Jun 21; ALS, 2 p. w/env
    [Discusses the ownership of a song sent by Carey; believes that the song underwent changes as it was passed down from one generation to the next.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to B[enjamin] H. [Ticknor], 1884 Jul 29; ALS, 1 p.
    [Reluctant to send in poems; feels that
    Nights with Uncle Remus
    and
    Mingo [and other Sketches in Black and White]
    were failures; believes poems will fail as well; is willing to release the firm from its agreement to print three books. Signed "Uncle Remus."]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to James R. Osgood, 1885 Mar 2; ALS, 2 p.
    [Says Ticknor unwell and acting strangely: requests an account of sales of unnamed Remus story and
    which he had already requested from Ticknor; chides him for refusing to publish J[ames] W[hitcomb] Riley's book.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to [Richard Waston] Gilder, 1886 Dec 21; ALS, 2 p.
    [Says that the ballad Mr. Smith referred to was an Afro-American song he published in
    some years ago; will send a copy; asks him to intervene in a dispute between Stoddard and Edgar Farwell in the Author's Club; claims that Mr. Buell is a womanizer.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to [Richard Watson] Gilder, 1887 May 26; ALS, 1 p.
    [Feels that Kemble is a suitable illustrator; urges Kemble to maintain the dignity of the Afro-American and to remember the differences of various Afro-American types.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to [Robert Underwood] Johnson, 1890 Mar 6; ALS, 3 p.
    [Comments on a lost list of names of people supporting a congressional bill; will send another list; suggests getting support for the bill from other less southern newspapers.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to [Robert Underwood] Johnson, 1890 May 8; ALS, 2 p.
    [Sends extracts from
    The Atlanta Constitution
    also hopes to get a statement in writing from his congressman.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to Unknown, 1891 Feb 13; ANS, 1 p.
    [Sends autograph; hopes the recipient and his boys will outgrow their bad habits.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to [Julius] Chambers, 1892 May 16; ALS, 1 p.
    [Requests scope and length desired for articles; lost the original letter that contains the terms for the new work; the articles will highlight the condition of the Afro-American in the South since the war.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to [Samuel Sidney] McClure, 1892 May 19; ALS, 2 p.
    [Accepts his proposition to publish a book in installments; declares that the illustration will be done to his own satisfaction; will create illustration in partnership with [Arthur Burdett] Frost; would like to get this matter settled soon.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to [Samuel Sidney] McClure, 1896 Mar 31; ALS, 2 p.
    [Requests further details from him for a short story because he had been busy.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to [Francis Jackson] Garrison, 1896 Oct 18; ALS, 3 p.
    [Discusses slavery in the South and his writings about the Afro-American; defends the relationship of the southern whites to the blacks.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to [Francis Jackson] Garrison, 1897 Jul 22; ALS, 4 p.
    [Discusses the theme and characters of the book
    Aaron in the Wildwoods
    . ]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to [Francis Jackson] Garrison, 1898 Mar 22; ALS, 3 p.
    [Discusses the illustrations for a Remus book by [Fred Stuart] Church and [Elmer Boyd] Smith; sends illustration of a fence designed to keep animals out of the garden.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to Paul R[evere] Reynolds, 1903 Mar 16; TLS, 1 p.
    [Has outlines for ten to fifteen Uncle Remus stories; asks for contact with the party who wanted two stories; mentions Mr. Shepard, the London artist.] (w/electrostatic copy
  - Joel Chandler Harris to Paul R[evere] Reynolds, 1903 Mar 20; ALS, 2 p.
    [Has a series of Remus stories in contemplation; will send them through McClure; asks Reynolds to return "A Romantic Tragedy" so he can make the necessary corrections.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to Paul R[evere] Reynolds, 1903 May 8; TLS, 1 p.
    [Asks him if he could sell six or eight more Remus stories to
    Collier's Weekly
  - Joel Chandler Harris to Paul R[evere] Reynolds, 1903 Jun 26; TLS, 1 p.
    [Inquires about the status of the ten Remus stories that he had sent for
    Collier's
    has another place for them if
    doesn't want them.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to Paul R[evere] Reynolds, 1904 Jun 2; TLS, 1 p.
    [Will send a story concerning a Union scout when finished; discusses requests for a book and some Uncle Remus stories.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to Paul R[evere] Reynolds, 1904 Jun 4; TLS, 1 p.
    [Asks him to secure English copyright on whatever work he receives from Harris; can furnish six stories to Reynolds if he wants them.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to Paul R[evere] Reynolds, 1904 Jun 10; TLS, 1 p.
    [Suggests that he should not wait for Russell to agree on a price for stories; might offer them to
    St. Nicholas Magazine
  - Joel Chandler Harris to Paul R[evere] Reynolds, 1904 Jul 23; TLS, 1 p.
    [Believes that Reynolds got a good offer from Mr. Russell; should complete the deal at once.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to Paul R[evere] Reynolds, 1904 Aug 12; TLS, 1 p.
    [Denies that British readers could not comprehend the Remus stories because they have been very popular in England; believes [Arthur Burdett] Frost is better than Verbeek at illustrating his stories.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to Paul R[evere] Reynolds, 1904 Aug 19; TLS, 1 p.
    [Mailing two stories; says the sixth and last story will be slightly delayed; reports that the
    New York Herald
    is undecided about asking him to write a story on Southern life.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to Paul R[evere] Reynolds, 1904 Sep 5; TLS, 1 p.
    [Received the check; comments on photo of a Mr. Russell taken with Anthony Hope. ]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to [Hamilton] Holt, 1904 Sep 22; TLS, 1 p.
    [Will contribute a series of articles and sketches for
    The Independent
    under the title "At the Sign of the Wren's Nest."]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to Mr. Miller, 1904 Oct 3; TLS, 1 p.
    [Will finish a story by the 15th; reexamining photographs and will send them in a few days.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to James H. Manning, 1905 Jan 17; TLS, 1 p.
    [Thanks him for letter and compliments; says Major LaRose is his wife's first cousin; autograph quotation of stanza of "At the Sign of the Wren's Nest" on verso.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to [Francis] Garrison, 1906 Oct 22; TLS, 3 p.
    [Gives some details of the recent riots in Atlanta; complains that most newspapers sensationalized these events; gives information on
    Uncle Remus's Magazine
    will control the editorial department and give a balanced view of life in the South.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to Colonel [John T.] Graves, 1907 Oct 30; TLS, 1 p.
    [Will be unable to fulfill his engagement this evening with Graves; compliments him on his career as an editorial writer; wishes him continued success in New York. ] (w/autograph corrections)
  - Joel Chandler Harris to [Richard Watson] Gilder, n.y. May 25; ALS, 2 p.
    [Recommends that lobbyists should be hired to promote the Congressional bill rather than sending literary men.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to Paul R[evere] Reynolds, n.y. May 25; TLS, 2 p.
    [Believes that the sale of serial rights includes all the available serial rights; asks that
    to arrange for simultaneous serial publication in England which would secure the English copyright for him.] (w/electrostatic copy)
  - Joel Chandler Harris to Paul R[evere] Reynolds, n.y. Jul 11; TLS, 1 p.
    [Authorizes him to secure serial publication and book rights to a series of Remus stories if possible.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to Paul R[evere] Reynolds, n.y. Jul 30; TLS, 1 p.
    [Terms made with Russell are satisfactory; AN at bottom says that he is enclosing "Brer Rabbit and the Gizzard Eater" which he has just published.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to Paul R[evere] Reynolds, n.y. Sep 23; TLS, 1 p.
    [Sending him the last of the Uncle Remus material.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to Paul R[evere] Reynolds, n.y. Oct 21; TLS, 1 p.
    [Inquires about his remittance for October.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to [Samuel Sidney] McClure, n.y. Oct 26; ALS, 1 p.
    [Has sent the manuscript for
    Aaron
    will have some additional stories in January.] (w/photograph of Harris attached)
  - Joel Chandler Harris to "Dear Madam", n.y. Oct 30; ALS, 2 p.
    [Discusses the publication of his latest book and critics' comments; will send a copy to Hayne when available; states preference for serialized publication of Remus stories in newspapers to their publication in book form.] (w/typescript copy.)
  - Joel Chandler Harris to [James Ripley] Osgood, n.y. Nov 14; ALS, 1 p.
    [Requests payment for royalty on sales of a Remus story and
    Mingo [and Other Sketches in Black and White]
    to July 1. Signed "Uncle Remus."] (w/typescript copy.)
  - Joel Chandler Harris to [Richard Watson] Gilder, n.y. Dec 2; ALS, 2 p.
    [Requests an extra proof of "Baalam and his Master"; sends a recent
    Constitution
    editorial for [Robert Underwood] Johnson; comments on the uselessness of sending literary men to Washington to push the copyright bill through Congress.]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to Charles A. Dana, n.y. Dec 11; ALS, 1 p.
    [Thanks him for his kind words about "Uncle Remus."]
  - Joel Chandler Harris to Samuel Sidney McClure, ALS, 1 p.
    [Writes that he is just finishing fifteen installments of Uncle Remus fables and asks what McClure will pay for the serial rights.] 1 p. (w/printed sketch of Harris)
  - Joel Chandler Harris to Unknown, ALS, 1 p.
    [Feels that he no longer wants to write "these legends."] (fragment)